[Subtitles by danielsangeo]
[gagging, gasping]
Had bad nachos again...
Have to tell everyone...there's bad nachos...
[coughing, gagging]
Aaagh...
REBEL: You're here!
[gagging]
WOMAN: Dr. Freeman?
Don't move. I'll kill you.
WOMAN: Gordon Freeman? Is that you?
What?
WOMAN: You've made it here this quickly?
WOMAN: Well, Eli is going to be
amazed--not to mention relieved.
There's not enough blood going to my head.
MOSSMAN: I'm Dr. Mossman, Dr. Judith Mossman.
Feels bad.
MOSSMAN: I've been hearing about you
since long before the Black Mesa incident.
Don't black out...
MOSSMAN: Ah, Black Mesa!
Don't black out!
MOSSMAN: I do so envy you...
Nnnghhhhh!
MOSSMAN: ...Dr. Kleiner when they
were at the top of their field.
Kleiner! Right!
REBEL: Here's where we turn
it all around, eh, Freeman?
Did he get you, too?! He's an animal!
[coughing]
MOSSMAN: I'll take you down
to Eli right away.
MOSSMAN: He would never forgive me...
So, did YOU gas me or was it her?
Answer me!
Never mind. It's actually not a bad idea,
and wouldn't have mattered
if I had my helmet.
So, once again, all roads lead to Kleiner.
MOSSMAN: We could certainly
use the extra help around here.
[growling]
MOSSMAN: We've covered a lot of
ground in the last few months,
MOSSMAN: but things would go so much faster
if we had more people with your training.
Yeah, that's kind of true
of everything these days.
MOSSMAN: We're closing in on a
reliable local teleport technology...
Oh, they KNEW it was unreliable.
MOSSMAN: ...something the
Combine still hasn't mastered.
They knew.
MOSSMAN: Eli thinks their
portals are string-based...
He's wrong.
MOSSMAN: ...similar to our Calabi-Yau model,
MOSSMAN: but they've failed to
factor in the dark energy equations.
Oh, you're one of THOSE.
MOSSMAN: They can tunnel through from
their universe, but once they're here...
"Universe"?
MOSSMAN: ...they're dependent
on local transportation.
MOSSMAN: If they know what
we're doing with entanglement...
Wait, it's a separate universe?
I'm going to have to see your math.
MOSSMAN: [laughs] Listen to
me. I sound like a post-doc.
Is this the only entrance?
MOSSMAN: I'm just so excited to think
MOSSMAN: that we'll finally
have a chance to work together.
Y'know, that's a real nice thought, but I
was followed. I don't think we're secure.
MOSSMAN: Oh yes. Dr. Kleiner compressed
the Xen Relay far beyond anything
Fuck...
MOSSMAN: he imagined at Black Mesa.
MOSSMAN: We've figured out how to
use Xen as an unexpressed axis--
OH!
MOSSMAN: --effectively a
dimensional slingshot...
There goes MY appetite!
MOSSMAN: ...come back in local space
without having to pass through.
What?! Are they serious?!
MOSSMAN: Oh! Here's Eli now.
Should I ask which one's Eli?
This is a nuthouse!
MOSSMAN: Eli! Look who
I found in the airlock.
It smells like sex in here.
ELI: Gordon Freeman! Heh.
ELI: Let me get a look at you, man.
Whoa, yeah. I definitely don't know you.
I would've remembered that leg.
ELI: Now let's see. The last time I saw you,
ELI: I sent you up for help
after the resonance cascade.
ELI: Heh, I never thought it would
take you this long to get back to me.
A lot of people died.
ELI: Welcome to the lab, anyway.
ELI: It's not Black Mesa, but
it's served us well enough.
MOSSMAN: It's going to be a lot more
like Black Mesa with Gordon here to help.
Well...
ELI: Right you are. MIT graduates
are few and far between these days.
Recognize!
ELI: We'll get you out of that hazard suit
ELI: and back into your
labcoat where you belong.
MOSSMAN: Let me just finish up some
work, and I'll see what I can dig up.
MOSSMAN: Dr. Freeman?
What?
MOSSMAN: It's been a real honor. I'm
looking forward to working together.
Well, I WOULD be except that we have--
ELI: Feel free to take a look around.
Yeah, listen. I was trying
to tell her I was followed.
Do you know if there's a w...
Okay, you're too old for
this. Who's in charge?
If you tell me it's the
alien, I'm leaving right now.
God, is this even real?
This is too nice! This isn't going to last!
You can't play with my emotions
like this! I won't let them!
MOSSMAN: Oh, Dr. Freeman.
You should stay with Eli.
Oh.
MOSSMAN: Go on. I'll be with you shortly.
This is good.
Okay, that's good you're
watching the kitchen,
but honestly, that's not enough.
We'll talk about that later.
Do you have a view of the exterior?
These look like they're somewhere else.
I mean if we see them coming, then
seconds matter. You know what I'm saying?
Dammit. Is that it?
MOSSMAN: Dr. Freeman?
What?!
MOSSMAN: I figured you and Eli would want
to talk about old times. We can talk later.
I don't know Eli.
Doesn't matter. You know how to use
the cameras. Watch the exterior.
Fuck! You're not even watching the outside.
ELI: Fine scientist, Judith. She
was up for your job at Black Mesa,
ELI: but you edged her out
with your Innsbruck experience.
Oh, I'm sure it was more than that.
Little Miss Dark Energy
hasn't impressed me so far.
Jesus Christ, I forgot about you.
Do I even want to know what you're doing?
Looks like monitoring software.
Or maybe he just hit the boss key.
No, don't look at me.
I'll deal with you later.
What the hell is this?
Is it one of their eggs?
It probably is.
There's going to be some changes
around here if we survive the night.
Okay, think, think.
The zappers aren't going to kill
me immediately. That's something.
"Earth Surrenders". Yeah, this
would've been useful earlier.
I can't focus...
The zappers are submissive now. They might
poison my food or kill me in my sleep,
but either way, I have time.
The troops will discover this place soon,
but if they sound a scout and we kill
'em, that might buy me half an hour.
Jesus, I can't even read this. I'm
going to need a new prescription.
That's another not-today problem.
ALYX: Oh, Gordon!
Oh my fucking god...
ALYX: The vortigaunts said you were here!
ALYX: I can't believe you
made it so quickly on foot.
Yeah, a LOT of people are
confused I'm still alive.
ALYX: Huh, he earned it. I guess you
proved you can handle yourself out there.
What's wrong you?
ELI: There's nothing Gordon can't handle.
ELI: With the possible exception of you.
That is very true.
ELI: Hahhhhh...
I don't blame the old man
for trying to pawn her off.
That's the same principle
behind hand grenades also.
God dammit! Why is everyone here so casual?!
It's like everyone is in denial.
This is the Lab of the Lotus-Eaters.
ELI: Take a look at this, Gordon.
[sighs]
Fine. What is it?
Oh god! I remember that!
You're trying to break my mind, old man?
Well, congratulations. You got my attention.
I think we should turn this off. How do
we know this isn't some sort of beacon?
Y'know, I never learned what went wrong
with the experiment; this is so dangerous!
Hey! How do you turn this off?!
Maybe this is his way of
getting me to shut up.
"Gordon, all you've done is
complain since you got here.
"How about I teleport your
ass back to alien hell?
"Bet you'd stop criticizing my lab, then."
All right, so I don't
really have any allies here.
I'm more like a zoo exhibit to them.
"Ooh! Look at the Freeman!"
Well, they're going to die.
MOSSMAN: Alyx, I thought you were on watch.
ALYX: The vortigaunts relieved
me so I could come see Gordon.
What?
ALYX: Anyway, I should be in
here working on the portal.
The aliens?
MOSSMAN: I have the repairs well in hand.
That's what you call the aliens?
MOSSMAN: Someone misjudged the
capacity of the Combine thyristor.
The vertigos?
ALYX: Are you blaming me?
Dammit.
MOSSMAN: No!
Not now!
MOSSMAN: Not at all. It was a calculation
error, not a mechanical problem.
You're not listening.
ALYX: Then maybe you should let
me do the calculations next time,
ALYX: as well as installing it.
MOSSMAN: Alyx, really...
Drama! Great...
MOSSMAN: Sometimes I think you
deliberately misunderstand me.
ELI: Ahem. Alyx, why don't
you take Gordon along
ELI: and give him some
practice with the gravity gun?
Wait...!
ALYX: Sure... Come on, Gordon.
Let's go have some fun.
No..!
MOSSMAN: The Zero Point Energy Field
Manipulator is not a toy, Alyx!
ALYX: Ugh. Let's get out of here.
Yes! Showing me the exits is probably the
best thing any of you can do at this point.
You're all too far gone.
One more time: I was followed;
this place is impressive,
but it's not NORAD;
they're going to find it, and kill you.
Bye.
And you! Do you even
understand what you did to me?
ALYX: So, I see you've met Dr. Mossman.
I guess not!
ALYX: She's one of the main reasons
I spend so much time outside.
ALYX: You should hear her drone on
ALYX: about how it should have been her
in the Black Mesa Test Chamber that day.
Oh, she said that?!
ALYX: I'm sorry. I shouldn't
be talking behind her back.
ALYX: It just gets a bit
claustrophobic down here.
Okay, so she's worse than I thought.
My god, it's the Ship of Fools down here.
ALYX: That's the old passage to Ravenholm.
What's that?
ALYX: We don't go there anymore...
But that IS an exit?
I can open it from here?
Okay, good, good. Keep
showing me stuff like this.
ALYX: Come on.
Oh, this is another one?
That's good. They probably won't come
from both sides without us noticing.
Though who knows? You left guard
duty to the vertigos, right?
They're probably out there
right now waving signal flares.
Okay, so do you want me to gas you?
I don't know what button to press.
God, I feel like I'm in the Twilight Zone,
and the twist isn't that the
Earth has been invaded by aliens.
It's that everyone left
is acting like an alien!
Everyone is acting WAY too calm!
It's not even optimism. It's just
a complete divorce from reality!
ALYX: So, here we are. The scrapyard.
That includes you, by the way.
Well...
I don't like this canyon at
all. It feels like a killbox.
ALYX: This is the gravity gun
my father was talking about.
At least it's quiet.
ALYX: You can call it the 'Zero Point Energy
Field Manipulator' if you really want to.
What?
ALYX: It's designed for
handling hazardous materials,
ALYX: but we mainly use it for heavy lifting.
ALYX: Give it a try.
Okay?  Why are...?
ALYX: The primary trigger emits a charge.
You can punt stuff and send it flying.
I missed something.
ALYX: I've found it handy
for clearing minefields.
Oh, it's for mines?
I have--WHUGH!
OH! That woke me up...
You sure I'm pointing this the right way?
ALYX: The secondary trigger
lets you grab things.
Oh...
ALYX: You can throw them with the primary.
Oh my god.
ALYX: Once you've picked something
up you can drop it gently--
Ah?!
ALYX: --by pressing your
secondary trigger again.
This is incredible!
ALYX: Pick up some stuff and toss it.
Okay, project...
[quickly exhaling]
UGH!
[coughs]
It feels like Jesus
shoving me out of heaven!
This changes gravity? There's
so many applications for this!
ALYX: You can also pull
stuff over from a distance.
Transportation, defense...
ALYX: Try grabbing those barrels
from that ledge up there.
That's a fair range.
What kind of battery does this
have? How long is the charge?
Huh-HOH!
ALYX: All right.
And now I want to press the
OTHER button, not the trigger.
Yeah.
This is astounding.
And all they're doing is
using this to move boxes?
ALYX: See if you can stack
some stuff to climb up here.
This is just a game for her, isn't it?
She has no contextual awareness.
I think she might have the mind of a child.
Okay, well...
I'll play along for now. I
need to see the exit anyway.
ALYX: Try stacking some things.
ALYX: Grab something with
your secondary trigger,
ALYX: then press the same
trigger again to drop it gently.
Yeah...
ALYX: All right.
She has to make sure she tells me
the rules--makes her feel important.
Yeah, look at her run. She's just a kid.
I don't even know if
I can be mad at her now.
This is all just a game of
Cops and Robbers to her.
Okay, we're in the future, so I
guess she grew up during this mess?
It must have stunted her development.
ALYX: Now let me call Dog.
He loves to play fetch.
Yeah, she's showing me her dog.
Christ, we gotta speed this up.
ALYX: Dog! Come!
What the fuck?
Hey, that's not a dog. Don't
know if you understand that.
Oh my god. We have a mech.
It's pretty mobile, too.
There's a lot of tech in this.
ALYX: Good doggie.
ALYX: Gordon, this is Dog.
ALYX: My dad built him to
protect me when I was a kid.
ALYX: First model was about yay-high.
Why isn't THIS on guard duty?
ALYX: Haven't I, boy?
ALYX: Okay, Dog,
let's play catch with Gordon.
Oh my god.
ALYX: You'll need to use the gravity gun.
This is such a long day.
ALYX: Go ahead, Dog! Throw!
Listen, I really am interested
in the engineering here,
but this isn't a good time for that.
I mean, we've clearly had a
battery breakthrough somewhere,
and this AI seems pretty good,
though I'd have to test it.
Yeah, see, now I'm getting distracted.
ALYX: Throw another, Dog.
No, we don't have time for this shit.
I'm not seeing an exit. Is
this just some giant sinkhole?
We need to kill these lights.
All right...
ALYX: Another one, Dog.
Why don't we play with Dog later,
because Uncle Gordon has some grown-up
things he needs to take care of?
Okay?
ALYX: Go ahead, Dog! Throw!
Well, it was worth a shot.
I don't want to make her cry,
but this is going nowhere fast.
We're lit up like a runway here.
ALYX: No, Dog!
Oh, damn, that's a lot of power!
And it looks like the AI isn't
much better than what we had.
[close explosion]
Whoa! I felt that!
[whistling sound]
[explosion]
OH NO! I WAS RIGHT! I WAS RIGHT AGAIN!
WHY AM I CURSED TO ALWAYS
BE RIGHT ABOUT EVERYTHING?!
I'M LIKE A MODERN GREEK TRAGEDY!
THEY'LL WRITE POEMS ABOUT ME!
[machine gun fire]
OH NO! NOT THE CHOPPER! NOT AGAIN!
I CAN'T TAKE IT! STOP IT!
Shut the door! Shut the door!
Go go go go GO!
C'MON, YOU FUCKING AI! IT'S
A BARREL, NOT A PERSON!
ALYX: This is Alyx, do you read?!
ELI: Alyx! Honey!
OPEN THE DOOR!
ELI: Where are you, Alyx?!
ALYX: We're in the scrapyard
airlock stuck in a full autocycle.
OPEN THE FUCKING DOOR!
ALYX: He's right here.
ELI: Good. I want you two to--
ALYX: Dad?!
You've gotta be kidding me...
ELI: Take Gordon out of
here! Head for the coast!
OPEN THE DOOR!
ELI: Do not go through Rav--
"Oh, wh-what was I saying?
Let me go find my glasses."
Your dad just killed us!
Yeah, just beat this thing
down. It's all we can do.
ALYX: Get it open!
I want to see some Three
Laws of Robotics rage.
Ohhhh, you got us into this mess and
you're going to get us out of it.
ALYX: Come on!
Y'know, I'm having a really
hard time staying positive!
If you told me you had a
secret submarine base here,
I think that would cheer me up.
[loud explosion]
OHH! AAH, MY LEG! MY LEG!
Aahhh...!
ALYX: Gordon, you need to get out of here!
Shit potatoes...
ALYX: I can't leave my father.
Aaah...
ALYX: Dog, take Gordon
to the Ravenholm tunnel,
ALYX: then circle around and
try to meet up with me. Hurry!
I could squeeze through that,
but y'know what?
Getting away from you is fine by me.
Can the AI actually understand all that?
Seems to. Wow.
Maybe it's working off of buzzwords.
I mean, AI is good until it's not.
Oh, radiation! Yeah, that's great.
Why is there so much radioactive material
in a hydroelectric plant, anyway?
Oh, damn, I should've checked to see if
it takes my voice commands or just hers.
That would've been a
nice going-away present.
Of course, that means it would
take enemy voice commands also,
but the odds they would be smart enough
to figure that out are basically zero.
But then they could say something like
"Flank left", and that could be a problem.
Yeah, I think it's a
bluff; there's no ticking.
What a day...
Y'know, I'm actually less nervous
now that the other shoe dropped.
WHOA! That solved THAT problem!
It's never too late to get shot, huh?
It's just...
Oh, okay. Maybe this is the equivalent
of those prop security cams that
are just there to scare burglars.
Or maybe this is backdoor surveillance, and
this place was infiltrated the whole time.
But am I being recorded?
OH! SHIT! I DO NOT GET A MINUTE,
DO I?! I DO NOT GET ONE MINUTE!
It just... It just heard me and
rolled the dice, hoping to land on me.
Fu...
This is going to be a
long night too, isn't it?
I should've just asked her to let me
ride the robot like a horse out of here.
She would think it's funny and
I would leave. Everybody wins.